hi I'm Brett curus uh I filmed this uh
video series um because I got an article
posted on strength coach.com and uh
people had some questions about the
exercise so this is actually the third
video of a four-part series the first
video series explained the uh supine uh
bridging progressions the second video
explained the prone and quadruped uh
progressions and then this one is going
to be the uh the abduction and external
rotation progressions a lot of people
don't know this they think the glutes
extend the hip and then the glute medius
and glute Minimus abduct the hip and
that's not true the uh the lower glutes
are just involved with hip extension but
the upper glutes actually do a lot of
different things they're they're
involved with hip extension and hip
hyper extension and also
abduction transverse abduction and then
external rotation which is like that so
these motions um and in fact the upper
glutes the upper gluteus maximus can get
uh targeted more from these movements
than they can from hip extension and hip
hyperextension exercises so these will
get your upper glutes firing to the
maximum degree but you have to know how
to progress so uh as uh as you you get
better at the abduction and and rotation
exercise you have to know how to load
them so I use bands you can also use
cables but the first uh and most basic
exercises would be the uh fire hydrant
and I got uh I tested the glute activity
of all these different exercises you
actually get more glute
activity when you do it this way where I
flex my leg and then come out
rather than if I just leave it like this
so Flex the leg and then come out try
not to twist okay and
then another basic one is the L
abduction and this one you don't want to
be leaning this way you want to be
leaning forward
slightly okay and then the third basic
exercise would be the sideline clam
don't have the legs back have them up
forward more and then
just open the legs
so uh it's pretty crazy these these
three exercises can activate someone's
upper glutes more than one rep max
squats lunges deadlifts in in a lot of
different people so remember the upper
glutes do a lot of different things the
lower glutes are just involved with hip
extension and hip hyperextension upper
glutes are very versatile okay so how do
we load these exercises I'm going to
show you three different ways the first
way is to
do standing hip
abduction
so and I can you know adjust the my
stance to make it easier harder but I
squeeze the
top okay that's one
way obviously um another way is to use a
band to do X band walks
but I actually don't like this that much
even though it gets me a good um pump it
really gets a burn in there that doesn't
get you too high on the glute Activation
so I don't use that one here's another
one the
seated band
abduction and this one here I
experimented with different stance with
and and you know you can go out wide
like this and really squeeze but
actually the best way is to get your
feet around shoulder width and
then come out like that
so really
squeeze okay so that's the seated band
abduction and
then this uh final exercise I call this
the band twist or the band rotation I'm
not trying to use my obliques I'm trying
to use the glute for this the upper
glute so all I do is I'm just going to
externally rotate and I can come you
know make it challenging
so I'm using the upper glue
so
um that concludes the um the uh external
Road ation and the abduction movements U
make sure you watch part one and part
two that show some of the the best hip
extension exercises and part four will
explain some of the myths behind
functional training and sports specific
training thank you